<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The royal law, or, The golden rule of justice and charity a sermon at the anniversary meeting of the gentlemen, inhabitants of London, and others, born within the county of Worcester, at St. Lawrence Church, Nov. 29. 1683.</title>
            <author>Boraston, George, b. ca. 1634.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 42 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A28812</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B3748</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9969</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11906822</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11906822</idno>
            <idno type="VID">50719</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A28812)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 50719)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 810:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The royal law, or, The golden rule of justice and charity a sermon at the anniversary meeting of the gentlemen, inhabitants of London, and others, born within the county of Worcester, at St. Lawrence Church, Nov. 29. 1683.</title>
                  <author>Boraston, George, b. ca. 1634.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Walter Kettilby ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to George Boraston. cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Dedicated to John Jolliffe, Francis Wright, Thomas Twittey, Thomas Clifford, John Harris, Richard Boraston, John Cooper, Thomas Thornbury, John Butler, William Butler, William Jefferyes, and Walter Bowyer.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Matthew VII, 12 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Monica Tsuneishi</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Monica Tsuneishi</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:50719:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The ROYAL LAW:</hi> OR, THE GOLDEN RULE OF Juſtice and Charity. A SERMON AT THE <hi>ANNIVERSARY MEETING</hi> OF THE Gentlemen, Inhabitants of <hi>London,</hi> and Others, Born within the County of <hi>Worceſter;</hi> at St. <hi>Lawrence</hi> Church, <hi>Nov.</hi> 29. 1683.</p>
            <p>By <hi>George Boraſton,</hi> M. A. Rector of <hi>Hever</hi> in <hi>Kent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Walter Kettilby</hi> at the <hi>Biſhop's-Head</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard. 1684.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:50719:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:50719:2"/>
            <head>To my Worthy Friends the STEWARDS for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Year.
<list>
                  <item>John Jolliffe,</item>
                  <item>Francis Wright,</item>
                  <item>Thomas Twittey,</item>
                  <item>Thomas Clifford,</item>
                  <item>John Harris,</item>
                  <item>Richard Boraſton,</item>
                  <item>John Cooper,</item>
                  <item>Thomas Thornbury,</item>
                  <item>John Butler,</item>
                  <item>William Bacon,</item>
                  <item>William Jefferyes,</item>
                  <item>Walter Bowyer.</item>
               </list>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THIS Sermon Preach'd at your Feaſt, is now at your requeſt made Publick, and preſented as an acknowledgment of your undeſerved Reſpects to me, and your kind Apprehenſions of the Diſcourſe it ſelf: It was not any opinion of the performance (to the weakneſſes of which I am not a little con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcious) that hath made me comply with your deſires to Print what I then Delivered; but an earneſt deſire and hope of Contributing in ſome meaſure to your Love, Veneration, and
<pb facs="tcp:50719:3"/>Practice of the Duties therein recommended, which ſo nearly concern the Vitals and Honour of Religion, and all the great Intereſts of Mankind; which great ends, if theſe Papers ſhall any ways promote, either in you or others, as you will have no cauſe to repent in deſiring, ſo neither ſhall I, in conſenting to the Publica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them; eſpecially ſince thereby I have the opportunity of Publiſhing to the World how much,</p>
            <closer>I am, <salute>Gentlemen, </salute>
               <signed>Your Humble Servant, and Affectionate Countryman, <hi>George Boraſton.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:50719:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>MATTH. 7.12.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>Therefore all things whatſoever ye would, that Men ſhould do unto you, do ye even ſo to them; for this is the Law and the Prophets.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>TO the performance of all thoſe Duties we owe to God or Man, we have no ſurer Guides, than thoſe natural notions interwoven in our make and conſtitution; and revealed Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, deſigned by infinite Goodneſs, and Wiſdom, to aſſiſt us againſt thoſe Weakneſſes, and to repair thoſe Ruins, we have contracted, by our vitious Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, our Evil cuſtoms, our Corrupt inclinations, our Imperfect and falſe reaſonings. Between theſe two, there's ſo fair and neceſſary a correſpondence, that it is to all conſidering Men, no ſlender ſupport of their Faith in things revealed, that they are ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to the common notices implanted in them by Nature.</p>
            <p>And yet in this unhappy age, we have a ſort of Men (Chriſtians I may not call them) who are as fond of Sacrificing Chriſtianity to their Luſts, as ever the Primitive Chriſtians were Zealous to Sacrifice their Luſts to the Laws of Chriſtianity, and their Lives for the Teſtimony of its Truth, and Excellency: Men who deſire to be known by the name of Deiſts, which
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:50719:4"/>is but a diſguiſe for an Atheiſt, ſince by it they well enough ſecure the effects of Atheiſm, even when they are aſhamed to own the principles of it.</p>
            <p>Hence it is they not only Quarrel and Affront, but Burleſque, and make Sport with the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; and if they durſt ſpeak out, would call the Goſpel a contrivance, and our Lord an Impoſtor. What elſe means that cried up aſſertion; that the Scriptures have no Authority, but what the Civil Power gives them? What elſe the revival of late of that long ſince baffled attempt,
<note place="margin">Philoſtr. life of Apollon.</note> by which <hi>Apollonius Tyanaeus</hi> that Impoſtor, and Magician, is made a Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rival, if not an Overmatch, to our Saviour, both in Miracles, and Sanctity of Life? And what is the drift, and ſecret tendency, and deſign of all this? But under the great reſpects they would ſeem to pay to the Law of Nature, to undermine, and juſtle all revealed Religion out of the World, and to ſet theſe two in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect oppoſition, and contradiction the one to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; that ſo they may thereby evacuate the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Law, and gain the greater Liberty and Scope in gratifying their Luſts; to which they imagine that to be a ſeverer Enemy, and to lay greater reſtraints on them, than the Law of Nature does. But by this, as well as other reaſons, it is evident, that it is not any ſtrength of reaſon, or conviction of their under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings, but a kindneſs to their beloved Luſts, that prevails over their minds, and influences their Faith, and makes them believe thoſe things, which are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicted by common ſenſe, and plain demonſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>For our Bleſſed Lord never deſigned to cancel the Laws of Nature, but every where ſuppoſes, and owns them, and ſuperſtructs Chriſtianity on that Baſis and Foundation. He intends not to diveſt Men, either
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:50719:4"/>of the principles, or paſſions belonging to Human Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, by converting them to Chriſtianity, or to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive them of ſuch helps, as either right reaſon affords them, or former Revelation had furniſhed them with, but to improve, and heighten both.</p>
            <p>The Law and the Prophets, were given by God, as a fuller, and plainer deſcription, and delineation of theſe natural Notions, and Duties which he hath Written and Engraven on our Hearts, which our Lord was ſo far from effacing or blotting out, that his deſign was to fill up, and compleatly finiſh that ruder draught, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and ſo to furniſh us with a perfect Picture of Virtue, in its full proportion; in its lively Colours; in its goodly and beautiful linea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; that ſo it might have that effect upon our minds, which <hi>Plato</hi> affirm'd, Virtue drawn to the life would have, if it could be ſeen, to wit, that it would kindle, and enflame, our affections, and raviſh our Hearts with its lovelineſs.</p>
            <p>This our Lord affirms of himſelf toward the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of this beſt of Sermons, St. <hi>Matth.</hi> Chap. 5.17. <hi>Think not that I am come to deſtroy the Law and the Prophets: I am not come to deſtroy, but to fulfil,</hi> that is, by adding other inſtances, by explaining it more fully, and intelligibly in many things and in more things reſcuing it from thoſe corruptions which the falſe gloſſes of the Scribes, and Phariſees, had mixt with it.</p>
            <p>'Twere eaſy to inſtance ſeveral Precepts in this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, in which he directs his hearers, and in them all Men, what to do as Men, and as Chriſtians, by ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing Moral and Political Virtues into Spiritual Graces.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:50719:5"/>
            <p>Of all which my Text may juſtly challenge the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedency; being the abbreviature of the Law of Nature; the Scope and Deſign of the Law and the Prophets; the moſt comprehenſive Rule, not only comprizing all thoſe Duties, that are uſeful for the conduct, and happineſs of Human Society, but alſo ſufficiently direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us to thoſe Duties, which we owe to God himſelf. For when we conſider his goodneſs towards us, and his kind uſage of us; ſparing us even when we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve puniſhment, and treating us with the affections and indearments of a moſt indulgent Parent; ſo that we our ſelves, cannot deſire or wiſh, that he ſhould do to us any otherwiſe, then he has done; his bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficence to us, and the good things he hath prepared for us, exceeding not only our greateſt hopes, but even the conceptions of our Hearts: I ſay, when we conſider this, we cannot but manifeſtly perceive our Obligations to the greateſt Veneration, Gratitude, and Thankſgiving imaginable, to ſo Gracious a Lord; to ſo obliging and adorable a Benefactor; in as much as we our ſelves do juſtly and reaſonably expect ſome proportionable returns, of thoſe, even of thoſe incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable benefits, we have conferred on others. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever I ſhall not treat of the words in this utmoſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, and latitude; but ſhall conſider them as they are an abſolute rule of our actions and dealings; enjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Charity and Juſtice towards all Men, in all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, and relations. A leſſon we are ſent to learn no further, and from no other Tutor, than our own breaſts; our own regular and well-governed deſires, what we are willing other Men ſhould do, or not do to us, are a ſufficient direction, and admonition, what we in the like caſes, ought to do, or not do to them: A Law written in ſuch legible Characters, that none can plead Ignorance, and of ſo eaſy a diſpatch, that
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:50719:5"/>the pleaſure that attends the performance, is a pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful invitation to indear, and a ſufficient reward to encourage our obedience; <hi>Therefore all things what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ye would that Men ſhould do unto you; do ye even ſo to them; for this is the Law and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In Diſcourſing of this Rule I ſhall obſerve three things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Law or Rule it ſelf, with ſome of its due proportions and meaſures.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Authority and Sanctions of this Law.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Some Irregularities, and deflections from this Rule, by which the purpoſes, and proper uſes of it are perverted.</p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>1. The Royal Law, or Golden Rule to be obſerved in all our Intercourſes, and Commerce,</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>All things whatſoever ye would that Men ſhould do unto you, do ye even ſo to them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A Law which is deduced from that common na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural inclination implanted in every one by God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; from whence it is, that every Man doth natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally ſeek his own preſervation, and welfare: That then which is naturally, and ſufficiently grounded in every Man, is laid there as a pattern for the exerciſe of Charity and Juſtice towards all other Men: For by this Native Law, we are obliged to deal with others, as if we had exchanged Perſons, and Circumſtances with them, and they were in ours. But then it muſt be remembred, that this ſelf-love, which is the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of our actings towards others, muſt be regular, and well-grounded in its ſelf; not meaſured by the diſordered appetites of every diſtempered mind, of every Vitiated and Exorbitant Will, which if once admitted, would ſoon introduce all the diſorders, and miſchiefs in the World;
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:50719:6"/>is the Original of all thoſe Sins, which make the times Perillous, overturns all Governments Sacred and Civil, throws all ranks and degrees of Men into Diſorder and Confuſion, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> obſerved long ago in his Epiſtle to <hi>Tim.</hi> 1 Epiſt. 3.1-5. The love then we owe to our ſelves, which is the meaſure of our actings to others, muſt be regular, and duly bounded, by recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied reaſon, common good, and to tend to an object re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally good. To give ſome plain inſtances of what we would, or would not have done to us; for the nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive is included in the affirmative. Do we abhor to be impoſed upon with Lyes, Mental Reſervations, and Equivocations? And are not we equally obliged; or can we without great partiality to our ſelves, not acknowledge our obligations, never to hide the true ſenſe of our minds, under any covert of reſerve, and ambiguous meanings? Is it by us reputed diſhoneſty in others, when they perform not their promiſes (thoſe more ſolemn ſecurities of Mens intentions) when they lawfully may or can? And ſhould not we be ever moſt punctual in performing our own? Do we ſtick to charge ſuch with Treachery, as well as Injuſtice, who in truſts committed to them, act not with the ſame fidelity, they would do for themſelves? And ſhould it not oblige us, in all truſts depoſited, to be ſo Faithful and Juſt, as never to abuſe the confidence repoſed in us? Would we have others take no advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of our ignorance, or neceſſity; ſo as to impoſe upon us either falſe Wares; or cheat us with fallacious weights and ballances? It certainly obliges us, that all fraud and deceit, all unjuſt weights and meaſures ſhould in our commerce be abominable to us, as the Lord ſaith they are to him?</p>
               <p>Do we in all our Straits (the common lot of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity being liable to ſuch portions of ſorrow) not
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:50719:6"/>only deſire, but lay claim to the compaſſions and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtances of others? And ſhould not this draw forth our bowels towards others; and move us to pour Wine and Oyl into their Wounds; to allay their Sorrows; to clear up their doubts; to remove their burdens; to Miniſter as we are able to the neceſſities of all who ſtand in need? Do we upon all occaſions deſire to be treated with ſweetneſs, and affability; that every pet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty provocation ſhould not raiſe, and break forth in ſtorms and rage againſt us; much leſs ſettle in rancor and malice; but rather that every one would be eaſy and forward to accommodation and all good offices? And ſhould not we go and do likewiſe? Are we ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of our reputation? Are we deſirous others ſhould be fair and candid Interpreters of our words and acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? And doth it not concern us to be ſo far from making havock of our Neighbours reputation; that we ſhould not ſo much as hearken to, or take up a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach againſt it? But ſhould be always ready rather to conceal a real fault, than be forward in divulging thoſe that are ſuppoſed only; and by the moſt chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table conſtruction, and faireſt Apologies, endeavour rather to render a great one leſs, then by ſly inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, perverſe reporting, and malicious ſuggeſtions to make a ſmall one great. Theſe are ſome of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſtrokes, and lines, meaſures and proportions of this excellent Law, whereby moſt of the caſes that occur, may with eaſe be determined, if our wills are not more deeply concerned than our underſtandings; which Rule is not more uſeful in it ſelf then Venerable and Sacred in its Authority which is my next conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>2. The Authority and Sanctions of this Law</head>
               <p> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, 1. A Law of Nature. 2. A Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:50719:7"/>the Prophets. 3. A Law of the great Prophet and Lawgiver himſelf.</p>
               <p n="1">1. A Law of Nature; a Law taken out of the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tices and Records of Nature, and moſt agreeable to it; providing ſufficiently for the neceſſities and equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly advancing the happineſs of Mankind; without which, we were not capable of receiving any Good, or avoiding Evil; but all private entercourſe and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Societies, muſt ſink into Ruin, and Confuſion. A Law of ſuch prime Evidence, that none can over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>look it; of ſuch apparent equity, that none can diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute it; viſible not only to Philoſophers and Wiſe-Men; but even to little Children; whom Nature it ſelf has taught, in all the petty injuries, and unkind uſages, which are offered to them, to rebuke the offender, with ſuch like words as theſe: You would not be will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing I ſhould ſerve you ſo; you would not willingly be ſerved ſo your ſelf. This is their ready and almoſt only protection and defence, to which on all occaſions, they have recourſe: This ſeems to be one of the firſt Efforts, and Sallies that their reaſon makes, and the only Rule to direct and guide their converſation with one another, and to ſecure themſelves from wrong: So open and obvious is the equity of this Rule, that it ſeems to lye uppermoſt in the principles of Human Reaſon.</p>
               <p>But then although this is a Law of ſuch apparent evidence, of ſuch undoubted certainty; yet becauſe of the ſhortneſs of Human Reaſon, and the uncertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of its deductions; and that what ſeems evident to ſome, to others ſeems inconſequent; and that the higheſt pretenders even in Mathematical and ſenſible demonſtration are ſometimes miſerably miſtaken (of which Mr. <hi>Hobs</hi> himſelf is a moſt ſhameful inſtance.)
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:50719:7"/>it would not be amiſs, if we had ſome infallible Guide, to ſecure us, even from the poſſibility of being miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken: This therefore is my next particular propoſed for the ſacredneſs of its Authority and Sanction, it being not the Law of nature only, but</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Law, and the Prophets.</p>
               <p>This Law is not only recommended to us by right Reaſon, but eſtabliſht alſo by Divine Authority, ſo that there is no poſſibility, either of doubting its Truth and Equity, or eſcaping from its Obligation. For who is there that dares queſtion the reaſonableneſs of that Duty to which Nature it ſelf prompts him, and the God of Nature directs him? What Chains can hold, what Fetters can ſecure that Man, who can break from two ſuch powerful ingagements, who will not ſubmit to two ſuch mighty inducements? To whom can we imagin that, that Man will hearken, who is Deaf to Natures kindly Voyce, and to that of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty Power. 'Tis true this Law <hi>in terminis</hi> oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curs not either in the Law, or in the Prophets, but there we may find others of the ſame import, of like equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valence with it; and in it are contained all the ſeveral Duties concerning the Juſtice and Charitableneſs of our deportment towards others, which are ſcattered up and down, and are more largely inſiſted on, in the Law and the Prophets. This is the Fountain from whence they all flow, and from whence they may without Tort, or Violence, be fairly deduced; the Center in which they meet, and to which they may with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruity be referred. This Rule contains in it the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and the equity upon which the numerous, and more particular inſtances of our Duty to others there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in preſcribed, is founded. This like an univerſal Soul, does permeate and run through them all, giving Life and Vigor, Force and Authority to them. The ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:50719:8"/>of humane Life, and the difficulty and tediouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Learning, and the intricacy of Knowledge, and the multiplicity of particular Caſes, Exceptions and Reſtrictions, has in all Arts, and Sciences, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended the uſefulneſs of ſhort Aphoriſms, of compendious Axioms, of little Summaries, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſive Abridgments, in which are contained the Subſtance, Pith, and Marrow of things; and which are as ſo many Pole-Stars to direct us in all our doubts, as ſo many Clues to guide and extricate us in the Labyrinths of Knowledge, in the variety, and Meanders of Human Affairs: Accordingly our good Lord, our gracious Lawgiver in Condeſcenſion to our infirmity, in Compaſſion to our Weakneſs, has in this Art of Godly living; this Art of Arts: Epitomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed our Duty, and compriſed in one eaſy and plain Rule, all thoſe numerous and ſometimes difficult pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, which are diffuſed, and are more largely com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented upon in the Law, and the Prophets; that ſo neither their intricacy might perplex and puzzle our minds, or their numbers burden and oppreſs our me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories; and both diſcourage our indeavours, and abate our induſtry. Would we know what the Law, and the Prophets in the ſeveral Periods of the World have delivered; would we behold it with one view, and caſt of the Eye? It is briefly comprehended in this ſaying: To this in all emergent difficulties, in all doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful perplexities, in new and unforeſeen caſes; when o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther means of reſolution are dubious, and intricate, or unſatisfactory, or quite fail us, we may have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe with the greateſt Eaſe, Security, and Safety: For if we will but conſult, and interrogate our ſelves, what it is we deſire, that others ſhould do to us in the like caſe, we cannot miſs of ſufficient information to direct our practice. Laſtly, As this is the Firſt, ſo it is
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:50719:8"/>the only Precept, to which our Lord has vouchſafed ſo high an Honour, has given ſo great a Character, that it is the Law and the Prophets. For that of love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our Neighbour as our Selves, and the like, to which this high Character is alſo aſſigned, is not different from it, but of the ſame purport, and equivalence with it: Only this before us, ſeems by far to have the preeminence of that; For, <hi>Thou ſhalt love thy Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour as thy Self,</hi> not only looks more imperative, and commanding without any reaſon annexed, or implied in it, to invite our love; but alſo by requiring it in ſo high a degree, and at firſt ſight in ſo ſeemingly impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible a meaſure, that it ſeems rather to deter us, and to render the Duty unpracticable. Whereas this by carrying ſuch apparent equity in its fore-head; by making our ſelves Judges in the caſe; and appealing to the natural ſentiments of our minds, does recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend it ſelf to our practice, and does ingage our hearts with the choiceſt endearments.</p>
               <p>But then Thirdly, Leſt any may imagine that this comprehenſive rule, that contains in it the Law and the Prophets, concerns thoſe only that lived under that diſpenſation; and that the men in the Text, are of that narrow extent, and ſignification, that our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour was under the Law; our Lord adopts this into his own Religion, and makes the Precept as Catholick as his Church; Nay, the truth is, it is of a much wider extent, and we have the warrant of his own expoſition (in the Parable of the Samaritan) to extend it, in a ſort to all men whatever, with whom we have any thing to do, or who live within the compaſs, and reach of our Charity. Accordingly his bleſſed Apoſtles do preſs this Duty on us, in this unlimited, and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal extent, exhorting us as we have opportunity, to do good to all men, to diſtribute liberally; to be
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:50719:9"/>Patient and Gentle; to abound in love; to make Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications, Interceſſions, and Thankſgiving for all Men. To which conſideration we may add, that this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of Love and Charity one towards another, is that command, which our bleſſed Lord did ſelect, and chooſe out, above all the reſt; every where thereto expreſſing a dear affection, a ſingular regard; claim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in it a ſpecial Intereſt, a peculiar Propriety; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commending, and preſſing the practice of it to his Diſciples, with an extraordinary concern, with urgent importunity, with unuſual Zeal; exemplifying, and outdoing the command in the whole tenor, and courſe of his life; having loved us not only beyond all for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer example, but alſo beyond all imagination and knowledge [<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Eph. 3.19.] urging, and enforcing our love to one another, from the conſideration of this exceſſivelove of his to us: Which that we may be in ſome meaſure able to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form and exerciſe, he hath given us his Holy Spirit to excite, and ſtir up, to ſhed abroad that Love in our Hearts, to multiply, and make it perfect in us. Which, what effect that loving Spirit hath upon us, how it is we behave, and demean our ſelves in the performance of this peculiar command; He in a ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal manner takes ſpecial notice of, and peculiar in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection, awarding to us our final Doom and Sentence, either of everlaſting happineſs or miſery, according as we have either conſcientiouſly, or negligently beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved our ſelves therein. So that if his commands, and example, if the aſſiſtance and aids of his Spirit; if the greateſt rewards to the obſervers, and ſevereſt denuntiations to the diſobedient, import any thing, the Authority is moſt Sacred, and the Sanctions moſt weighty. And though it is ſo Sacred, in its Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; though in its ſelf ſo neceſſary, to the welfare of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:50719:9"/>mankind, yet how miſerably it is wreſted and perver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, will appear in the conſideration of,</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>Thirdly; Some irregularities, and deflections from this Golden Rule, </head>
               <p>whereby the right purpoſes, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per uſes of it, are perverted. Some willingly claim an intereſt in the firſt part of the Rule, but reject the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; would have all do well to them, but themſelves not obliged to do good to any. Not unlike ſome narrow Factions in Religion, who take all acts of Grace done to them, as their due, and therefore can never be thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for any; but when power is gotten into their hands, can breath forth nothing but ruin, Root and Branch, to all that diſſent from them. Such is the Iſſue of that lewd Doctrine, Dominion is founded in Grace.</p>
               <p>Others live and act as if the Rule run, <hi>All whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ye would, that do ye;</hi> theſe do not bend their Wills to the Rule, but bow the Rule to their Wills; as if our Primitive State were indeed what Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi> fancied it, a State of War in which every one hath right to all things; that Power only gives right, and is the meaſure of Juſt and Honeſt; and that Men were to live on the Land, as Fiſhes do in the Sea, the greater to devour the leſs, and more helpleſs fry. Some multilate the Rule, or clog it with ſuch a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſo our great Lawgiver never intended, they put out, <hi>As ye would they ſhould do unto you;</hi> and read it, <hi>as ye are done unto,</hi> though never ſo unjuſtly and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitably: They act not by the meaſures of juſt, and regular appetites, but of other Mens Evil demea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor towards them, contrary to the true temper of the Law, and Spirit of the Goſpel, which is ſo far from allowing the leaſt revenge in caſe of injury, and wrong received, that on the contrary, it not only commands us to forgive the Offender, but alſo to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige him; to return him love for hatred; Bleſſing for
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:50719:10"/>Curſing; good Offices for deſpiteful uſage; Prayers and Interceſſions for Mockery and Perſecution, St. <hi>Matt.</hi> 5.44.</p>
               <p>This is the Nobleſt, the Beſt, the only revenge al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed us; beſt in regard of our Enemy, whom by this means, if by any, we ſhall either convert, and gain, or mollify and ſweeten; beſt for our ſelves, who by ſo doing ſhall become the Sons of God, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble our Heavenly Father, in his exceſſive goodneſs, in his exuberant Beneficence, in his unparallelled Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanthropy. Again ſome leave out <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, all things whatſoever, and put in <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſome things, and to ſome ſort of perſons. In leſſer things, they are contented to be exactly juſt, and merciful, but then they are not uniform in greater; when ſome conſiderable damage may be avoided, or advantage acquired, they muſt be excuſed, be the means never ſo indirect; the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages of the end, and the great emolument, and the goodly purchaſe they expect and hope for, will accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their opinion, and Goſpel, be ſufficient to Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy the means, be they never ſo unjuſt and uncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. And as their Juſtice and Charity is thus narrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and crampt to ſome things, ſo alſo their huckſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing kind of Love is confined to ſome Men, that is, Men of their own Party. Some Mens Religion in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects their minds with ſuch a four leaven, that they look upon the reſt of Mankind as reprobates; and will hardly allow their Chriſtian Friends or Governors, if they are not of their way and Faction, a room in their Prayers. This Partiality hath been the bane of the Churches Peace, the chiefeſt cauſe of moſt of thoſe Schiſms, and Differences, under which Chriſtendom hath from time to time, and doth ſtill groan; this hath thruſt the Flock of Chriſt into a far narrower com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs than ever the Donatiſts did, concluding the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:50719:10"/>of Saints only to their Sect or Party. And no wonder this uncouth humor hath got into their civil commerce and dealings, who if they do not think it their intereſt, to Trade only with ſuch, yet think Mercy and Juſtice owing only to them: So that a Phariſaical Corban ſhall evacuate thoſe Duties towards all other Men; and as they are apt to reckon it no Duty to exerciſe Juſtice and Mercy to them, ſo they are no leſs forward to account it no Sin, to defraud and over-reach them. Among this latter ſort of Men, if we may judge of them by their practice, I fear ſome reckon the King himſelf, whoſe cuſtoms they dare ſo frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſteal, without any conſcience of the greatneſs of the Sin: Though the King hath as undoubted a right to them, as any Subject hath to the eſtate he poſſeſſes; yea, though our Lord himſelf, for whoſe commands and example they profeſs ſo great a reverence, was at the charges of a Miracle, to pay <hi>Caeſar</hi> his Cuſtom; from whence we may ſafely infer, he would never have given his Vote to diſenable <hi>Caeſar</hi> to pay his debts.</p>
               <p>But let ſuch Men be aſſured the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, though of infinite Vertue and Value to peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, will never ſerve their turn, nor anſwer for this, or any other act of Injuſtice, without reſtitution, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their ability. You have heard what this Law is with ſome of the principal meaſures and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portions of it; the ſacredneſs of its Authority; and the miſerable perverting of it to ill purpoſes from its proper uſes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <p>What now remains, but that as we eſteem and look upon the Creed, as a ſhort Summary, comprehending the Fundamental Articles of our Religion, in reference to our Faith; in like manner, we take this Royal Law, as a brief <hi>Compendium</hi> for the direction of our Practice? That we by no means allow our ſelves in any courſe or
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:50719:11"/>action, which this Golden Rule diſallows; that we be at all times ſo far from invading other Mens Rights, whether in their Lives, Liberties, Reputation, or E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, that we rather account it our happineſs, as it is our Duty, to be ſenſible of their Diſtreſſes, and ſtoop to their Neceſſities, when we ſee any Afflicted; to gratifie them with our Beneficence, when we ſee them in any kind or degree to ſtand in need of it; to bear patiently with their offences, if they forget themſelves ſo far as to do us any; to be ſo far from of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering any Injury, that we will not return the greateſt, unleſs it be with Prayers and Interceſſions, and all kind Offices; never to uſe our power to oppreſs, or skill to deceive any that deal with us, or who repoſe any Truſt in us; to be more afraid to take away another Mans Goods, Life, or Reputation [which is dearer than Life] unjuſtly, than to loſe our own.</p>
               <p>And give me leave [Worthy Countrymen] to hope, that to ſpeak Truth; to perform your Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; to be ſaithful to your Truſts; to act without Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe; to be ſincere and upright in all your Dealings; to do the utmoſt good, and bear the greateſt Injuries without Retaliation, are things ſo Sacred in themſelves, and by you as ſuch eſteemed and looked upon; that you will rather ſuffer the loſs of any thing, than be falſe to any of your Obligations. Yea give me leave to believe, your Meeting this Day to be no leſs than a living Comment upon my Text; that you are tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing into your Practice the Characters of Primitive Chriſtianity, when Truth and Honeſty, when Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Charity, were not only acknowledg'd Duties, but in faſhion alſo; that, as I perſwade my ſelf, you are exactly juſt in all your Intercourſes, ſo the deſign of your Feaſt, is not ſo much any Oſtentation of your Riches, Plenty, and Magnificence, as a Teſtimony to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:50719:11"/>God of your thankfulneſs for what you enjoy; not for exceſs and luxury, but for the promoting of this Law of Love and Friendſhip among your ſelves; and which is Godlike too, and the beſt return you can make to God, to make others partake of your Plenty, to change Conditions and Circurnſtances with them, who want what you enjoy, by the real exerciſes of your Charity to them. But if any among us can act con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to this Royal Law of Juſtice and Charity, let them</p>
               <p n="1">1. Recollect with what Conviction, and ſhame many Heathens will riſe up in Judgment, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn ſuch Chriſtians.</p>
               <p>Shall <hi>Marcus Antoninus</hi> the Heathen Emperour, and <hi>Philoſopher,</hi> propoſe to his own breaſt that Queſtion, What is that we muſt beſtow moſt of our Care and Dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence upon, and anſwer himſelf, even upon this on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that our Minds and Wills be Juſt; that our Actions be Charitable; that our Speech never be Deceitful? And ſhall Chriſtians be negligent and careleſs of the Juſtice of their Minds and Wills; of the Charity of their Actions, and the Integrity of their Words? Shall an Heathen have ſo great reverence for Truth, that he would not allow a Lye to be ſpoken, no not in jeſt? And ſhall Chriſtians be lovers and makers of Lyes; and Lying among them, be made an Holy Artifice? Shall an Heathen tell us that he is the worſt of Villains, who will deceive that Man, who had been ſafe, if he had not truſted him? And ſhall not only private, but publick truſt, and even for pious uſes too, be loſt careleſly, be embezel'd prodigally, or converted to their own uſes by Chriſtians? Shall the Clerks of the Market in Heathen <hi>Rome</hi> enact, that whoſoever ſold any Commodities, ſhould diſcover their faults to the Buyer; that falſe Weights and Wares ſhould be caſt
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:50719:12"/>into the River, and mulcts, or corporal puniſhments ſhould be inflicted on the Offendor? And are Deceits and Frauds, falſe Weights and Ballances, Myſteries of Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, not only practis'd, but continued in notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the rebukes of their Conſciences? Shall an Heathen cauſe his Servants continually to attend him with great Sums of Mony, that by the readineſs of his relief, he might not leave any appearance of the leaſt denyal, by the delay? Shall the ſame Heathen frequently cover thoſe he ſaw in poor and ragged Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, with his own? And ſhall Chriſtians ſee others who partake of the ſame Nature and Redemption with them, naked and not clothe them, hungry and thirſty, and not feed, and give them to drink? Shall an Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then when that Man was in his power, who malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly had put out one of his Eyes, be ſo far from re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venging the Injury; that beſides the courteous uſage of him, he never gave over his friendly Counſels, till he had made him in love with Philoſophy, and had inſtructed him in the Principles and Rules of the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieſt Life? Shall another Heathen [as the ſame Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, <hi>Origen</hi> in his laſt Book againſt <hi>Celſus</hi> relates] when one ſaid to him, let me periſh if I do thee not a miſchief, anſwer him, and let me periſh if I do not my utmoſt to make thee my friend: And ſhall the Lives and Language of Chriſtians be full of animoſities and ſourneſs, ill offices, revenge and hatred? Shall an Heathen Prince reverence Chriſt and Chriſtianity, for this ſaying in my Text, ſhall he cauſe it to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graven on his Plate, written on the Walls of his Palace, and Courts of Judicature? Shall He ſometimes in his own Perſon, at other times by an Officer, when Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefactors were puniſh'd, ingeminate this expoſtulation, while the puniſhment was inflicted; Wouldſt thou have this done to thy ſelf, and thy own poſſeſſions,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:50719:12"/>which thou haſt done to another; thereby to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince them the more fully of the Iniquity of their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and the Equity of their ſufferings? And ſhall Chriſtians be ſo far from making uſe of ſuch appoſite means of imprinting this excellent Rule in their own and others memories; of recalling it to their minds; of declaring their high eſteem and value they have for it; that on the contrary, either through Sloth or Negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, they ſeldom or never think of it, or elſe through vitious practice, endeavor to efface and obliterate it out of their minds? Once more, ſhall the <hi>Lex Julia</hi> in Heathen <hi>Rome,</hi> allot the ſame puniſhment to Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and Treaſon; and <hi>Marcellus</hi> a great Stateſman, lay it down for an undoubted Rule, that Subjects may wiſh for good Princes, but ought to bear with any? And ſhall theſe who ſeem to own Chriſt under the greateſt demonſtration of ſelf denyal, count Sacriledge no Sin, and a deſign of riſing againſt their Soveraign no Treaſon; and be ſo far from bearing with Evil Governors, that they Libel, Defame, Perſecute, and thirſt after the Blood of the beſt? With what face can any Chriſtian appear before the Righteous Judge, who hath greater aids and obligations, and doth leſs; more Grace, and yet lives worſe than an Heathen? As not an ordinary Confuſion will cover their faces, ſo an ordinary Hell will not ſerve the turn of ſuch prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Chriſtians. Eſpecially</p>
               <p n="2">2. When they ſhall remember that the Name of Chriſt is more diſhonor'd by ſuch pretenders, than by thoſe who declare open hoſtility againſt him. Did a Man deſign to Stabb his Religion deeply, and do as great deſpite as malice it ſelf could contrive to the Founder of it, he could not take a more effectual way to do both, than to make high pretences to tenderneſs
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:50719:13"/>of Conſcience in leſſer things, and ſhew great Zeal for God and the myſteries of Religion, and yet be Kna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh, Unjuſt and Uncharitable in his dealings. I doubt not to ſay that few conſiderations have more contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to the Irreligion and Debaucheries of the Age, than the known prevarications of many, who have made great profeſſions of Religion, but yet have lived in the practice of Sacriledge, Sedition, Rebellion and Perjury, taking Oaths contrary to their former, and breaking all, as they ſerved, or diſſerved their intereſt. Without doubt Orthodox manners are the beſt demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, as well as the greateſt Honor of Orthodox belief; Men know not what we believe, but they know what we do, and by that will judge what we believe, and what we are; ſtrangers and ſtanders by are eaſily tempted to believe that there is no Religion, or that Religion is nothing, when they ſee that the moſt Zealous pretenders to it are not only careleſs in obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, but living even in open and direct contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to its Precepts. May I add,</p>
               <p n="3">3. That the practiſe of theſe Duties is the ſureſt evidence of our being good Men, approved of God, Favourites of Heaven, Citizens of <hi>Sion;</hi> for theſe Duties being regularly performed include Faith in God as their great root and principle, are thoſe Graces which as they do derive from God, ſo they do moſt aſſimilate and recommend us to him who is moſt juſt and merciful: And what better evidence can there be of a Mans being good, than being moſt like to, and approved by him who is perfectly ſo? And as it would be an evidence that we are good Men, ſo it would make us peaceable Chriſtians, for</p>
               <p n="4">4. It would have a mighty tendency [which all
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:50719:13"/>good Men Wiſh and Pray for] to allay our heats about notional Doctrines and Circumſtantial things, which ſerve only to diſtinguiſh Clans and Sects, and expoſe all that is dear to us, to thoſe, whom we cannot gratify more [could we ſee it] than by our diviſions. But theſe Duties, as they are ſuch in which all are agreed, ſo were we as careful in the conſcientious practice of them, we ſhould have both leſs liſt, or leſs leiſure to find faults, and hunt after ſcruples, or raiſe needleſs, and unprofitable diſputes; or if any did ariſe, they would be manag'd ſo amicably, that the Peace of the Church ſhould not be diſturb'd by them. And as it would make us Peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Chriſtians, ſo it would alſo</p>
               <p>Laſtly, Render us Loyal and Obedient Subjects: Inſtead of turning Politicians, and Stateſmen, medling with things above our Sphere, and Plotting with our heads; we ſhould ſtudy to be quiet, and to do our own buſineſs, and work with our hands. We ſhould be as forward to render <hi>Caeſar</hi> his due, as we are to demand our own; we ſhould be as tender of invading or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croaching on his undoubted Prerogative, as we are ſcrupulous of preſerving our own unqueſtionable pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges; we ſhould obey our Superiors, with the ſame willing ſubjection, with which we deſire our Children, and Servants ſhould obey us. We ſhould have their perſons in great Veneration, and Honor for their high Office and Character which they bear; we ſhould put a fair and candid conſtruction on all their actions, and make a juſt allowance for the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avoidable miſcarriages they are liable to; conſidering the arduous, and intricate affairs, which they are to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage; the ſubtle intrigues to which they are expoſed; the unforeſeen difficulties that ariſe; the uncertainty of Human affairs; the many and great tentations,
<pb facs="tcp:50719:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>with which they are a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>aulted; we ſhould never Quarrel, much leſs grow Turbu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>t, and Seditious upon the account of ſmall miſcarriages which are inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to the beſt of Governments.</p>
               <p>To ſay no more, this would verify and make good that Propheſy concerning the peaceable and happy condition of Chriſts Kingdom, that the Lyon ſhould lie down with the Lamb, that we ſhould beat our Swords into Plough-ſhares, and our Spears into pruning Hooks, that our Nation ſhould not lift up Sword a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our Nation, nor ſhould we learn War any more.</p>
               <p>This World would be as quiet an Habitation as it can poſſibly be, and it would make us as happy in our ſelves, Dutiful to our Superiors, helpful and propiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous one to another in all our converſe, as we can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire or wiſh; It would be the beſt Human means to recover this Sinful Nation, and oppreſſed Church, from the Miſeries Spiritual and Civil, under which they groan: However let what will be our lot in this World, it will undoubtedly ſecure us an intereſt in a better, which God of his infinite mercy, for the ſake of his Son, through the aſſiſtance of his good Spirit, grant us. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
